[SPEAKER_01]: So, the suttas I'll read right now are concerned with thinking and thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: The first sutta is in the Majjhima Nikaya, number 19, and it's called Two Kinds of Thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus have I heard, on one occasion, a blessed one was living in savarthi.
[SPEAKER_01]: There he addressed the bhikkhus thus.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bhikkhus, venerable sir, they were glad.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Blessed One said this, because before my enlightenment, while I was still only an unenlightened bodhisattva, it occurred to me, suppose that I divide my thoughts into two classes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then I set on one side thoughts of sensual desire, thoughts of ill-will, thoughts of cruelty, and set on the other side thoughts of renunciation, thoughts of non-ill-will, and thoughts of non-cruelty.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I abided thus, diligent, ardent, and resolute, a thought of sensual desire arose in me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I understood thus.
[SPEAKER_01]: This thought of sensual desire has arisen in me.
[SPEAKER_01]: This leads to my own affliction, to the other's affliction, and to the affliction of both.
[SPEAKER_01]: It obstructs wisdom, causes difficulties, and leads away from nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: When I considered this leads to my own affliction, it subsided in me.
[SPEAKER_01]: When I considered this leads to others' affliction, it subsided in me.
[SPEAKER_01]: When I considered this leads to the affliction of both, it subsided in me.
[SPEAKER_01]: When I considered this obstructs wisdom, causes difficulties, and leads away from nibbāna, it subsided in me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whenever a thought of sensual desire arose in me, I abandoned it, removed it, and did away with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I abided thus, diligent, ardent, and resolute, a thought of ill-will arose in me.
[SPEAKER_01]: A thought of cruelty arose in me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I understood thus.
[SPEAKER_01]: This thought of cruelty has arisen in me.
[SPEAKER_01]: This leads to my own affliction, to others' affliction, and to the affliction of both.
[SPEAKER_01]: It obstructs wisdom, causes difficulties, and leads away from nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: When I considered thus, it subsided in me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And whenever a thought of cruelty or ill-will arose in me, I abandoned it, removed it, and did away with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this... this... obviously, I just want to point out that he was a bodhisattva.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, someone who was inclined towards enlightenment, who is...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, towards enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you also... and... so, he clearly knew what nibbāna was.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, as I said, it leads away from nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you already had the understanding of what nibbāna is, and then you decided, what if I divide my thoughts in these two categories?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, basically, you can also say these two categories is the thoughts that lead away from nibbāna, and the thoughts that don't lead away from nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thoughts that lead away from nibbāna are thoughts of sensuality, ill-will, and cruelty.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thoughts that don't lead away from nibbāna are thoughts of non-sensuality,
[SPEAKER_00]: Non-ill will and non-quilt of renunciation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, nibbāna is something to be understood, which is why understanding brings you closer to it, and then developing your mind in regard to that understanding, basically, makes you sort of abide in nibbāna, like an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm saying this because most, most commonly, nibbāna is understood as some sort of transcendental
[SPEAKER_00]: Out of this world state that you kind of stumble upon, if you have luck, if you've been if you've been trying hard enough, then it happens to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basic.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a practice of understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Understanding what nibbāna is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Understanding what dispassion is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seeing it is valuable.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the most important thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seeing it is peaceful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seeing it is worthy.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then developing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Developing nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Developing nibbāna, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And another thing to point out there, it's essential thought arose in me.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, essential thought would have arisen in Bodhisattva or in somebody who practices, and he recognized it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It arises on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's not on him.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is on him is wrongly attending to it, attending it as valuable, attending it as dear, delighting in it, wanting it, proliferating it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But turning your mind away from it, then the thing would disappear.
[SPEAKER_00]: So he would see, oh, this is harmful to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is not pleasant or agreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: It leads to my harm, it leads to harm of others, it leads to harm of both.
[SPEAKER_00]: And ultimately, it leads away from nibbāna, which is the ultimate goal.
[SPEAKER_00]: So there would be enough, and then that thought would go away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the mind would genuinely not want it, which means then it has arisen on its own accord, and then it has ceased.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it hasn't been... You know, somebody turns up in front of your door, and he's unwelcome, and then he leaves, because he realizes he's unwelcome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, it continues.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because whatever a bhikkhu frequently thinks and ponders upon, that will become the inclination of his mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: If he frequently thinks and ponders upon thoughts of sensual desire, he has abandoned the thought of renunciation to cultivate the thoughts of sensual desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then his mind inclines to thoughts of sensual desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: If he frequently thinks and ponders upon thoughts of ill-will, upon thoughts of cruelty, he has abandoned the thoughts of non-ill-will or non-cruelty to cultivate the thoughts of cruelty or ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then his mind inclines to the thoughts of cruelty.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just as in the last month of the rainy season, in the autumn, when the crops thicken, a cowherd would guard his cows by constantly tapping and poking them on this side and that, with a stick to check and curb them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because he sees that he could be flogged, imprisoned, fined or blamed, if he let them stray into the crops.
[SPEAKER_01]: So too, I saw in unwholesome states, danger, degradation and defilement.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in wholesome states, a blessing of renunciation, the aspect of cleanser.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I abided thus, diligent, ardent and resolute, a thought of renunciation arose in me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I understood thus.
[SPEAKER_01]: This thought of renunciation has arisen in me.
[SPEAKER_01]: This does not lead to my own affliction, or to the other's affliction, or to the affliction of both.
[SPEAKER_01]: It aids wisdom, does not cause difficulties, and leads to nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I think and ponder upon those thoughts, even for a night, even for a day, even for a night and day, I see nothing to fear from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But with excessive thinking and pondering, I might tire my body.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when my body is tired, the mind becomes strained.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when the mind is strained, it is far from composure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I studied my mind internally, quieted it, brought it to singleness, and composed it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: So that my mind should not be distrained.
[SPEAKER_01]: Likewise with the thoughts of non-irrelevant thoughts of non-truth.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, bhikkhus, whatever a bhikkhu frequently thinks and ponders upon, that will become the inclination of his mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: If he frequently thinks and ponders upon thoughts of renunciation, he has abandoned thoughts of sensual desire, to cultivate the thought of renunciation, and then his mind inclines to thoughts of renunciation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the next simile, just as in the last month of the hot season, when all the crops have been brought inside the village, villages, a cowherd would guard his cows, while staying at the root of a tree, or at, or out in the open,
[SPEAKER_01]: Since he needs only to be mindful that the cows are there, so too there was no need for me... there was need for me only to be mindful that those states were there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Tired... tireless energy was aroused in me and unremitting mindfulness was established.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he didn't have to trace them individually.
[SPEAKER_01]: My body was tranquil and untroubled, my mind composed and uniform.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he goes into the jhānas.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, first, a person needs to know what nibbāna is, which basically means a person needs to develop samādhi, needs to get the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once the right view is there, all the person has to do is divide his thoughts into wholesome and unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Into those that lead away from nibbāna and those that lead towards nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why Mahāpajāpati came to the Buddha and said, oh, can you give me a short instruction and I'll go on a retreat deep in the forest.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he said, whatever you know it's wholesome, whatever you know it's unwholesome, abandon it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever you know it's wholesome, cultivate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: In terms of the thinking, and it's exactly the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, with the right view, all you need to do is divide the thoughts into categories and stick to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, sometimes it's going to be hard work, as much as it is to guard your herd from like, don't go too much left, don't go too much right, don't go into this crop, don't go into that crop, because you'll end up in serious trouble.
[SPEAKER_00]: But once that's done, then all you need to know, herd is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you sit under the tree, on top of a hill, and see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: No problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not going anywhere, because there's nothing pulling them now.
[SPEAKER_00]: All the crops are gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they're just, just, just, just kind of at ease, sitting on a field, and you can see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that means, oh, you're not... you have so much energy now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Such a peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: No worry, no distraction, not tired.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you're established upon it, and that is the pleasure of jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, for instance, the thoughts of renunciation, you don't have to be cultivating...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...thoughts of renunciation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, now I get it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The cultivation basically comes down to saying no to sensuality, saying no to a will, saying no to cruelty.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you get established upon that, it's just there, and that is effortless.
[SPEAKER_00]: And knowing that, then this whole joy and the unremitting mindfulness and tireless energy arises.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, the thoughts are there.
[SPEAKER_00]: The thoughts that are not thoughts of sensuality, not thoughts of ill-will, not thoughts of corporate.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by having just these thoughts there, you know, ah, those unwholesome thoughts cannot enter.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're dispelled.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they said, usually, people were trying to cultivate thoughts of kindness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, he actually just just kind of gave me another point to say.
[SPEAKER_00]: People who try to cultivate practice of jhāna, inverted commas, sought to then not have sensuality and not have this, but that needs to be abandoned beforehand, through wisdom and clear seeing, and then you enter the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when these, like, quite secluded from unwholesome states, as every description of jhāna says, then the mind gets settled in that, established, and then he enters and abides in that jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I was saying earlier today, then he can, once his mind is abiding in jhāna, then that's another sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: He walks around, he urinates, he defecates, he extends his arm, he does this, and his mind is in that jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's secluded from unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like deer in a mosquito-free marsh.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, or like monks in a mosquito-free marsh.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like right here.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the point is then, once such level of uninterrupted clarity is established, with the right view, which means with knowledge of what nibbāna is, then the mind gets developed knowledge, further and further and further, as that sukha will go.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that enters and abides in nibbāna and meets finish.
[SPEAKER_00]: No more asuras to come back, and it's done.
[SPEAKER_00]: In nibbāna, it's not hard to understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's subtle, because people's minds are too far away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they revolve around sensuality, ill-will and cruelty.
[SPEAKER_00]: But nibbāna literally means absence of greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means absence of passion, cooling down of all the passions you can imagine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Subtle, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, even Pūrṭujā can get his head around that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if he was to stick to it,
[SPEAKER_00]: Stick to avoiding unwholesome, stick to virtue, stick to sīla, stick to all of those other things that would be conducive towards his idea of dispassion, then he will actually clarify that idea more and more.
[SPEAKER_00]: And with further reading of the suttas and input from from the Buddha or from if he has a living arahant or a living sotāpanna, even better, but even without it, he would actually come close and then, yeah, that's what nibbāna is and get the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it will require, obviously, quite a great deal of mind development, of sticking to the, you know, not, not, not letting your, your, your mental thoughts, your, your herd wander into the crops.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't mean saying no to everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to say no to things if it doesn't involve sensuality, if it doesn't involve cruelty, if it doesn't involve real world.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you certainly need to be very mindful of it, because it might involve sensuality, it might involve the world, it might involve the whole world.
[SPEAKER_01]: I always bring affliction to myself, to others, does it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Does it?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it doesn't bring affliction to me, not to others, not to both.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay then, but even then, you don't eat negligently.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't give in to it with negligence.
[SPEAKER_01]: But with, like, sensual dissolve?
[SPEAKER_01]: Sexual intercourse, you say, will this bring affliction to myself?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, like the other sutta, that is to be completely abandoned.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no ground whereby sexual intercourse or sensuality of that kind would, oh, can be done mindfully or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: We can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can eat mindfully, you can sort of come across sight, sound, smell, taste, touch mindfully, but sexual intercourse cannot be done mindfully.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that needs to be abandoned.
[SPEAKER_01]: Entanglement.
[SPEAKER_01]: Difficulties.
[SPEAKER_00]: And fundamentally, as I said before, as the suttas said before, the one we read, you can't have sensuality without being bound by sensual perceptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry, you can't engage in a sexual intercourse without being bound by sensual perceptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you can't say, I'm free from sensuality and then practice sexual intercourse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there is no sexual intercourse without your mind being bound by sensual perceptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if the mind is bound by sensual perceptions, well, that is as far from nibbāna as it can be.
[SPEAKER_01]: The sūtra ends with one of my favorite things.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha says, there are these roots of trees, these empty huts,
[SPEAKER_01]: Meditate, Bhikkhus, do not delay, or else you will regret it later.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, Bhikkhus, you have the right view, you know what nibbāna is, now go to these empty dwellings, roots of trees, forests, mountains, and practice, develop further clarity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't be negligent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you've always got it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that sutta ends, and that is what the Blessed One said, because we're satisfied and delighted in the Blessed One's words.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's another sutta on the same subject of thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the next one, Madhyamakāya's.
[SPEAKER_01]: 20.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Removal of Distracting Thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus have I heard, on one occasion, that Blessed One was living in Sarvatthi.
[SPEAKER_01]: There He addressed the bhikkhus thus.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bhikkhus.
[SPEAKER_01]: Venerable Sir David Blunt, the Blessed One, said this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, when a bhikkhu is pursuing the higher mind, from time to time, he should give attention to five signs.
[SPEAKER_01]: What are the five?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because, when a bhikkhu is giving attention to some sign, and owing to that sign, there arise in him evil, unwholesome thoughts, connected with desire, connected with hate,
[SPEAKER_01]: With delusion, then you should give attention to some other song connected with what is wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he gives attention to some other sign connected with what is wholesome, then any evil unwholesome thoughts connected with desire, with hate, and with the delusion are abandoned in him and subside.
[SPEAKER_01]: With the abandoning of them, his mind becomes steady internally, quieted, brought to singleness and composed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just as a skilled carpenter or his apprentice might knock out, remove, or extract a coarse peg by means of a fine yarn, so too, when a bhikkhu gives attention to some other sound connected with what is wholesome, his mind becomes steadied, internally bighted, brought to singleness, and concludes.
[SPEAKER_01]: If while he's giving attention... Let me just address...
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, obviously, the main thing that emerges from this, it's understanding the nature of the sign.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the mind arises on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: You attend to its aspects.
[SPEAKER_00]: And based on the aspects you're attending, based on the signs, signs and tokens, as often we say, in the circles.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's like a general notion in regard to the arisen mind, to the arisen thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: By attending to them, then you might be contributing towards more of the unwholesome thoughts, or towards going back to the wholesome thoughts, depending on what you choose to attend to.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the point is to recognize it's... it has like a slightly indirect nature, in a sense that you're not trying to deny what has arisen in your mind, or you're trying to deny what mood your mind is in, what the general state mind is in.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not denying that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just recognizing that by attending to something else, it will drift away from that, if that was unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: If that was wholesome, then it's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: You keep your watch on it, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if it's wholesome, that doesn't mean you become negligent, as I said just a minute ago.
[SPEAKER_00]: You keep watching, but it's... now it's effortless, because you don't need to take it away from you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's... it's... it's like... like a... like a... again, a simile of a cow herd, that you have to keep an eye on.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the cows see the green crops, well, they will be very inclined towards... then you have to hold them back, and that's hard work, and it's tiresome.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you then foresee the sign of the green crops.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will disturb, they will excite the cows.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you direct them somewhere else, in a different direction, where they won't see the green crops, and then they'll be calm, because there's nothing exciting it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you'll be at ease, because you don't have to work hard to keep it away from the crocs.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just as simple as turning to something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you recognize, by being in such an environment, or by thinking certain things, well, the mind will get excited.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You look at the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: You focus on the opposite, so then the mind calms down.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's important to have that sign of that mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: To recognize it for what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's an independent animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not you, because that would imply that, like, direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, sorry, direct kind of control of it, which you don't have.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has a reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have indirect responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: By bringing your cowherd foolishly in front of a green crop, what do you expect is going to happen?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you foresee that, and you don't put them there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You put them somewhere else, maybe behind the corner, where they can't see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, they might smell it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Every now and then, if the wind blows in their direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, you refine the signs and tokens you pick on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, they don't see it, but if the wind blows, they smell it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, you do it in a different way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you block the smell, or you light the fire, so the smoke kind of obscures the smell, or various things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Point being, you recognize the mind as an independent animal that needs kind of catering and watchful eye.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, true.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you take it away from sensuality and bring it closer to nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: The sutta continues.
[SPEAKER_01]: If while he's giving attention to some other sign connected with what is wholesome, there still arise in him evil unwholesome thoughts connected with desire, with hate and with delusion, then he should examine the danger in those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: These thoughts are unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: They are reprehensible.
[SPEAKER_01]: They result in suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he examines the danger in those thoughts, then any evil, unwholesome thoughts connected with desire, with hates and with delusion are abandoned in him and subside.
[SPEAKER_01]: With the abandoning of them, his mind becomes steadied internally, quieted, brought to singleness and concentrated.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just as a man or a woman
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when simply directing away from whatever was unwholesome is not enough,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you have to make more of an effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whereby, you start dwelling on the dangers of letting cow go into the crop.
[SPEAKER_00]: Imprisonment, trouble, difficulty, fine, basically, the dangerous sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, like, gives you more, well, more motivation to take it away from that which, which excites it.
[SPEAKER_00]: This will take your mind away to bring it to dispassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If, while he is examining the danger in those thoughts, there still arises in him evil and wholesome thoughts connected with desire, with hate and with delusions, then he should try to forget those thoughts and should not give attention to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he tries to forget those thoughts and does not give attention to them, then any evil unwholesome thoughts connected with desire, with hate, and with delusion, are abandoned in him and sapsang.
[SPEAKER_01]: With the abandoning of them, his mind becomes steadied internally, quieted, broad, synchronous, and composed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just as a man with good eyes, who did not want to see forms that had come within range of sight, would either shut his eyes or look away.
[SPEAKER_01]: So too, when a beggar tries to forget those thoughts and does not give attention to them, his mind becomes steadied, internally quieted, brought to singleness and composure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, back to the using the cow simile, cow head.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you've taken the cow away from the... from seeing the crop.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no smell of the... of the... of the fresh grass, fresh crop, disturbing them anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're tied down to the ground.
[SPEAKER_00]: You keep an eye on them, but basically, they're still excited, because they still have the memory of the crop.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then you just sit down and ignore them, because you know, well, they can't get there, because you took them away.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're secured wherever they are away from the crop.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just ignore them, because they will calm down, and then they calm down.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't fuss around, because it disturbs you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You recognize, okay, you needed to fuss around until there was still a danger of them going into the crop.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now you've done, you removed that that possibility, now just ignore it and they'll come down.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like being in a secluded little forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like foreseeing they're going into the forest, there won't be any sensual disturbances.
[SPEAKER_00]: You go to a forest.
[SPEAKER_00]: You take your mind into the forest by basically walking your body there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you leave your mind, your body there, which means your mind is bound with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, your mind has to be in that forest, in that environment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, it will calm down.
[SPEAKER_00]: There might be memory or the perceptions of excitement or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: But sooner or later, it calms down.
[SPEAKER_00]: It forgets about.
[SPEAKER_01]: If while he is trying to forget those thoughts and is not giving attention to them, there still arise in him evil unwholesome thoughts connected with desire, with hate and with delusion, then he should give attention to the stilling of the thought determination of those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he gives attention to the stilling of the thought determination of those thoughts, then any evil unwholesome thoughts connected with desire, with hate and with delusion are abandoned in him and subside.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just as a man walking fast might consider, why am I walking fast?
[SPEAKER_01]: What if I walk slowly?
[SPEAKER_01]: Then he... he would walk slowly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then he might consider, why am I walking slowly?
[SPEAKER_01]: What if I stand?
[SPEAKER_01]: Then he would stand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then he might consider, why am I standing?
[SPEAKER_01]: What if I sit?
[SPEAKER_01]: Then he would sit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, he might consider, why am I sitting?
[SPEAKER_01]: What if I lay down?
[SPEAKER_01]: And he would lay down.
[SPEAKER_01]: By doing so, he would substitute for each grosser posture, one that was subtler.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that point, or that step, so to speak, basically, that's the step that goes beyond wholesome and unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because addressing unwholesome, addressing dangerous with wholesome, didn't work.
[SPEAKER_00]: The threat is still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that step pertains to the nature of thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stealing that which determines the thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: That which every thought has in common, be it wholesome or unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what every thought has in common is movement as a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: On a level of images, of mind, there is a movement.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you recognize, okay, they want to move in this direction, I take them, I move them into this direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, they want to move, they still want to move the other direction, then I ignore the movement, then I do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, when none of that works, then you start refining the nature of the movement.
[SPEAKER_00]: As a result of that, the course
[SPEAKER_00]: Movement that's being... sorry, the core sensuality that's being carried with a coarser form of movement is being sieved out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you're walking fast, which is what sensuality is, basically excitement, you slow down and then there is no room through that refined movement for a coarser movement of sensuality to come through.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you refine it further and further and further until it's still and it doesn't move.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there is no sensuality, there is no disturbance, there is no excitement without mental movement.
[SPEAKER_00]: There can be a mental movement without that particular excitement.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why you use mental movement, the refining of the mental movement, so to abandon that particular unwholesome excitement.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then the mind comes out of that singleness, that stillness,
[SPEAKER_00]: But the excitement is gone, and then you can go back to the normal, whatever, daily movement of a wholesome thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: To do this, you obviously have to be able to see your mind still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even to do the first step, you need to have the sign of your mind, which means you need to have the right view again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that section sounds like...
[SPEAKER_01]: I've heard others explain it, that one should think slowly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, like, I am going to get up...
[SPEAKER_00]: In a way, you are kind of slowing down your... Well, you're refining your thoughts, you're slowing down the movement of your thoughts, but you're not slowing down your discernment or your clarity.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're slowing down the intentions?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not necessarily.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your intention is to get rid of the unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still very much present.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you're refining.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're basically seeing unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is the unwholesome thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a movement within that thought that's dictated by that unwholesome, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can say like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is an unwholesome moving thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Refine that there is a moving thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Refine that there is a thought, still thought, that doesn't move.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you start seeing
[SPEAKER_00]: Within the movement of the unwholesome thought, and then within that, and then within that, and then within that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that stillness, and that's quite... requires clarity, and a clear notion of the sign of the mind, sign of the thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not saying to, like, slow down your thought, but actually, just discern a more general
[SPEAKER_01]: Phenomenon, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Within that thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what really pertains to the nature of the thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The unwholesome moving thought, wholesome moving thought, they share the... in a particular aspect, they share the same nature of a moving thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, moving thought of the... pertaining to unwholesome, moving thought pertaining to wholesome, you can take it further.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is... what do they have in common?
[SPEAKER_00]: They are moving thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: What does any moving thought, no matter of the movement, has in common?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you're saying, you're looking at a subtler...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, that's what it says.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm walking fast.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why am I walking... Why is this body being moving fast?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why don't I slow it down?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why don't I stand?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why don't I have the body in a non-moving position?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not running fast, start walking slowly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not walking slowly, standing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not standing, sitting down.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not sitting down, laying down.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what all of those postures have in common?
[SPEAKER_00]: They're all body.
[SPEAKER_00]: They all pertain to the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you're refining in terms of the movement, in terms of the engagement.
[SPEAKER_00]: Subtler and subtler and subtler.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, the thread of the clarity of pertaining to the thought, or pertaining to the mind, or pertaining to the intent of abandoning unwholesome, remains.
[SPEAKER_00]: That thread stays through all of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, you use it to abandon the unwholesome movement of your thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: When nothing else worked, you use it, basically, until
[SPEAKER_00]: The unwholesome falls off, and then, okay, now you can start moving again, if you want, if there is a need for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It continues.
[SPEAKER_01]: If while he is giving attention to the spinning of the thought determination of those thoughts, there still arise in him evil unwholesome thoughts connected with desire, with hates, and with delusion,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, with his teeth clenched and his tongue pressed against the roof of his mouth, he should beat down, constrain and crush mind with mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: When, with his teeth clenched and his tongue pressed against the roof of his mouth, he beats down, constrains and crushes mind with mind, then any any evil unwholesome thoughts connected with desire, with hate and with delusion are abandoned in him and subside.
[SPEAKER_01]: With the abandoning of them, his mind becomes steadied, internally quieted, brought to singleness and composed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just as a strong man might seize a weaker man by the head or the shoulders and beat him down, constrain him and crush him, so too, when with his teeth clenched and his tongue pressed against the roof of his mouth, a bhikkhu beats down, constrains and crushes mind with mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: His mind becomes steadied, internally quieted, brought to singleness and composed.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's quite a false view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: When nothing else works, you still refuse to allow cowherd to go into that crop.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, no matter how hard it is, it's still not as hard as then, enduring the punishment, once they've got gone into the crop.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you have to, you then just basically put a rope and just, just, just pin them down until they come down.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it will exhaust you, but still the purpose will be fulfilled.
[SPEAKER_00]: Keep the cowherd away from the green fox.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it has to calm down.
[SPEAKER_00]: They can't... they themselves will tire out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you just make... make your determination stronger, longer lasting than their determination.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's quite a simple thing to understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you can see this is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you just stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what people don't understand then, the pain, the sharp pain that will come, seemingly, because of the restraint, the fear, the panic, the neurosis, everything else that comes, that's all part of that cow's herd rebellion.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all part of the weaker man's...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you don't know he's a weaker man.
[SPEAKER_00]: Until here comes down, based on your grip, then you know you're stronger.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you'll find out you're stronger, if you prevail.
[SPEAKER_00]: But people usually, when it comes down to restraint, and then the pain comes, and then the fear,
[SPEAKER_00]: Various emotions now being caused by... you become more sensitive or whatever else, then people start developing lots of views on account of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Views that take them away from a quite simple, this is wholesome, this is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start justifying or you start giving in.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you do need the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: To not give in to that, because anybody can practice restraint, but restraint in itself does not lead to the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: It aids the right view to fulfillment, but it cannot bring you the right view by itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, if you don't know what nibbāna is, you can't possibly know what comes closer to it, what drifts away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you clarify as much as you can with what nibbāna is, and then you start emulating the behavior, mental states, actions of that which is in nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Acting like an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Acting like an arahant, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like, well, I'm not an arahant yet, so I can't do... No, you can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you want to...
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're not an arahant yet, means you need to act like an arahant harder.
[SPEAKER_00]: And yeah, you know, it might break somebody.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want people up to such a point that they crack.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's the real risk.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's hard to say, like, act like an Arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it doesn't mean act like an Arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Act in front of others.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means, like, don't tolerate anything unwholesome in your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't tolerate anything unwholesome in your mind, you won't be able to engage in anything unwholesome by your speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you can't engage in anything unwholesome with your speech, you can't do anything unwholesome with your body.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean go around, you know, acting loftier than everybody
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Act like an arahant means emulate arahant in your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this is the ending of the sutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when a bhikkhu is giving attention to some sign and only to that sign there arise in him evil unwholesome thoughts connected with desire, with hate, and with delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, when he gives attention to some other sign connected with what is wholesome, any such evil unwholesome thoughts are abandoned in him and subside.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he examines the danger in those thoughts, when he tries to forget those thoughts and does not give attention to them, when he gives attention to the stilling of the thought determination of those thoughts,
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, when, with his teeth clenched and his tongue pressed against the roof of his mouth, he beats down, constrains and flushes mind with mind, any such evil thoughts, unwholesome thoughts are abandoned in him, and his mind becomes steadied, internally quieted, brought to singleness and composed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, this bhikkhu is then called the master of the courses of thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: He will think whatever thought he wishes to think, and he will not think any thoughts that he does not wish to think.
[SPEAKER_01]: He has severed the craving, flung off the fetters, and with the complete penetration of the conceit, he has made an end of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is what the Blessed One said, and the bhikkhus were satisfied and delighted in the Blessed One's words.